Guide to the Collection of Bookplates by George W. Eve
Yale University Arts Library
Collection of Bookplates by George W. Eve
1886-1950
1891-1912
BKP 124
Yale University Arts Library
1.25
(3 boxes)
This collection contains over two hundred bookplates by British designer and etcher George W. Eve (1855-1914).
Eve, G. W. (George William), 1855-1914
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Yale Bookplate Collection was formerly housed in Sterling Memorial Library. The collection was incorporated into the Arts of the Book Collection in 1984 and then moved to the Seeley G. Mudd Library in 1990. In 2011, it was transferred to the Robert B. Haas Family Arts Library.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
George William Eve (1855-1914), a British bookplate artist, was an etcher and an expert in the field of heraldry. He was admitted to the Heralds' College as well as to the Royal Society of Painter-Etchers and Engravers. He produced a number of armorial bookplate designs, including a series of three bookplates for the Royal Library at Windsor Castle, which were used by Queen Victoria. Many of his designs were exhibited in Great Britain as well as internationally. He was also the author of Decorative Heraldry; A Practical Handbook of Its Artistic Treatment, published in 1897.
Reference: George H. Viner, A Descriptive Catalogue of the Bookplates Designed and Etched by George W. Eve, R.E. (Kansas City: The American Bookplate Society, 1916), 13-16.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains over 200 bookplates by British designer and etcher George W. Eve (1855-1914). Most of these bookplates are documented in A Descriptive Catalogue of the Bookplates Designed and Etched by George W. Eve, R.E., authored by George H. Viner and published in 1916. Given his background and expertise in heraldry, most of Eve's bookplates are armorial designs, although several fine pictorial designs, such as library interiors and maritime scenes, are also included.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Bookplates – Numbered. II. Bookplates – Unnumbered. III. Bookplates Attributed to Eve. IV. Correspondence and Ephemera.
Bookplates; Bookplates; Eve, G. W. (George William), 1855-1914
- Bookplates – Numbered, Series I
  Arrangement
  Arranged numerically by checklist number – roughly chronological in order. Any correspondence or ephemeral materials relating to a specific bookplate are filed together with the bookplate.
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes bookplates that are identified and numbered according to the descriptive catalogue published by George Heath Viner in 1916.
  - #1 Sir Henry Allsopp, 1886; 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - #2 William Flory, 1891; 4 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - #3 Everard W. Barton, 1892; 3 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - #4 A. R. Motion, 1892; 2 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - #5 Dr. Astley Phillips, 1892; 10 items (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - #6 Frederick Bernard Senior, 1892; 2 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - #7 William Henry Weldon, 1892; 8 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - #8 George Douglas, Duke of Argyll (Campbell), 1893; 3 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - #9 George Ravenscroft Dennis, 1893; 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - #10 "Metuenda Corolla Draconis", 1893; 3 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - #11 Sir David Evans, K. C. M. G., 1893; 4 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - #12 William Henry Weldon, 1893; 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - #13 Algernon Sidney Bicknell, 1894; 4 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - #14 Philip Wm. Poole Britten, 1894; 2 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - #15 R. E. H. Duke, 1894; 4 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - #16 Stewart Beauchamp Gwatkin, undated; 3 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - #17 Howel J. J. Price, 1894; 4 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - #18 E. Tautz, 1894; 1 (Box 1, Folder 17a)
  - #19 Sir John Nicholson Barran, 1895; 10 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - #21 Elizabeth Anne Bostock, 1895; 3 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    This folder contains five letters written by Eve and addressed to Miss Bostock, dated 1904-1905.
  - #22 Henry Farnham Burke, 1895; 2 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - #23 James Frederick Chance, 1895; 3 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - #24 William Swaine Chisenhale-Marsh, 1895; 3 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - #25 George Edward Cokayne, undated; 3 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - #26 Everard Green, 1895; 9 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - #27 Richard Southcote Mansergh, 1895; 4 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - #28 Richard Southcote Mansergh, 1895; 3 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - #30 [Weldon], 1895; 2 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - #31 William Henry Weldon, undated; 4 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - #32 C. V. S. Downes, 1896; 2 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - #33 Thomas Greer, 1896; 5 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - #34 Georgii Alexandri Lockett, 1896; 3 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - #35 John W. Walker, 1896; 3 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - #36 William Farrer, 1897; 3 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - #37 J. J. Howard, 1897; 8 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - #38 Juliani Marshall, 1897; 7 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - #39 Platt-Higgins, 1897; 1 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - #41 Windsor Castle Library, 1897; 1 (Box 1, Folder 36a)
  - #42 Cirencester, 1898; 2 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - #43 James Bruce, 1898; 1 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - #44 Charles Drury Edward Fortnum, 1898; 4 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - #45 Richard R. Holmes, 1898; 2 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - #46 Richard R. Holmes, 1897; 3 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - #48 John Lawrence Langman, 1898; 1 (Box 1, Folder 41a)
  - #49 Philip Lawrence Langman, 1898; 10 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - #50 Ludwig Neumann, 1898; 3 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - #51 Reginald Pole-Carew, 1898; 2 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - #52 Sir James Reid-Bart, 1898; 2 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - #53 Windsor Castle Library, 1898; 1 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - #54 Windsor Castle Library, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    This folder contains an ex-libris of Annie Yorke mounted together with #54.
  - #55 Mary Rensselaer Lee Cassilly, 1899; 2 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - #56 William Kyle Westwood Chafy, 1899; 4 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - #57 Dorothy Crisp, 1899; 3 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - #58 Frederick Arthur Crisp, 1899; 9 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - #59 Margaret Crisp, undated; 4 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - #60 Ursula Crisp, undated; 3 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - #61 Sir Charles Jessel, 1899; 3 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - #63 Constance, Countess of Derby (Stanley), 1899; 1 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - #64 Anna M. Thompson, 1899; 10 items (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - #65 W. Bruce Bannerman, 1900; 12 items (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - #66 Herbert Cokayne Gibbs, 1900; 4 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - #67 University of Liverpool, undated; 6 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - #68 G. H. Ryan, 1900; 5 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - #70 Buchanan Winthrop, 1900; 3 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - #71 Birkenhead Public Library, 1901; 2 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - #72 Una Fielden, 1901; 2 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - #73 Henrici Dni de Aldenham, 1901; 1 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - #74 Arthur Dashwood Howard, 1901; 3 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - #75 Robert Mackworth-Praed, 1901; 3 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - #76 S. P. M. Maryon-Wilson, 1901; 9 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - #77 Henry Portman, 1901; 3 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - #78 Edward Stone, 1901; 3 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - #79 John Morris Stone, 1901; 2 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - #80 W. Heward Bell, 1902; 2 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - #81 Charles John Philip Cave, 1902; 4 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - #82 Laura Mary Foster, undated; 3 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - #83 Frances Evelyn, 1902; 5 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - #84 Richard George Penn, Earl Howe, 1902; 2 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - #85 Sir Reginald Pole-Carew, 1902; 1 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - #86 Ida, Lady Shuckburgh, 1902; 3 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - #87 Windsor Castle Library, 1897; 1 (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - #88 Windsor Castle Library, 1898; 3 (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - #89 Windsor Castle Library, 1898; 2 (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - #90 Bannerman, 1903; 8 (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - #91 W. Bruce Bannerman, undated; 4 (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - #92 Sir James de Hoghton, 1903; 2 (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - #93 George James Lind, 1903; 7 (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - #94 John Madden, 1903; 3 (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - #95 John Clements Waterhouse Madden, undated; 2 (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - #96 Royal Societies Club, 1903; 9 (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - #97 Sir Francis Reginald Wingate, 1903; 4 (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - #98 Walter Cave, 1904; 4 (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - #99 James Charles Getting, 1904; 9 (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - #100 James Charles Getting, undated; 13 (Box 2, Folder 91)
    This folder also contains several letters written by Mr. Getting between 1908 and 1918.
  - #101 Tyson of Woodhall, 1904; 3 (Box 2, Folder 92)
  - #102 Edward Bond, 1905; 5 (Box 2, Folder 93)
  - #103 A. H. F. Boughey, 1905; 5 (Box 2, Folder 94)
  - #104 Hugh Bright, 1905; 7 (Box 2, Folder 95)
  - #105 Robert & Beatrice Irene Bush, 1905; 3 (Box 2, Folder 96)
  - #106 John Brainerd Capper, 1905; 4 (Box 2, Folder 97)
  - #107 Richard Edward Goolden, 1905; 4 (Box 2, Folder 98)
  - #108 Winfred Porter Truesdell, 1905; 6 (Box 2, Folder 99)
  - #109 Victor Albert George, 1905; 2 (Box 2, Folder 100)
  - #110 George H. Viner, 1905; 5 (Box 2, Folder 101)
  - #111 Ethel Rimington Wilson, 1905; 4 (Box 2, Folder 102)
  - #112 George Abraham Crawley, 1906; 4 (Box 2, Folder 103)
  - #113 Mary Leslie Crawshay, 1906; 1 (Box 2, Folder 104)
  - #115 Archibald Lawrence Langman, 1906; 3 (Box 2, Folder 105)
    This folder also includes a letter written by Eve and addressed to Mr. Langman, dated 1902.
  - #116 Leeds University, undated; 1 (Box 2, Folder 105a)
  - #118 Helen Atherley, 1907; 2 (Box 2, Folder 106)
  - #119 J. W. L. Glaisher, undated; 5 (Box 2, Folder 107)
  - #120 Nora [Goldsmid], undated; 1 (Box 2, Folder 108)
  - #121 Sir John Lawrence Langman, 1907; 5 (Box 2, Folder 109)
  - #122 James Joseph Pearce, undated; 1 (Box 2, Folder 110)
  - #123 Margaret Elizabeth Jersey, 1907; 2 (Box 2, Folder 111)
  - #125 Lucy H. Boileau, 1908; 2 (Box 2, Folder 112)
  - #126 Maurice C. Boileau, undated; 1 (Box 2, Folder 113)
  - #127 Dorothy Campbell, undated; 1 (Box 2, Folder 114)
  - #130 Institution of Electrical Engineers, 1908; 2 (Box 2, Folder 115)
  - #132 Charles Edward Ellis, undated; 2 (Box 2, Folder 116)
  - #133 Inez Blanche Ellis, undated; 1 (Box 2, Folder 117)
  - #134 Alan Frederick Gardiner, undated; 2 (Box 2, Folder 118)
  - #135 Henry Stuart Maclean Jack, 1908; 3 (Box 2, Folder 119)
  - #137 R. Cyril Lockett, 1908; 2 (Box 2, Folder 120)
  - #138 Richard Cyril Lockett, 1908; 3 (Box 2, Folder 121)
    This folder also contains an example of #137 mounted together with #138.
  - #139 Consuelo Manchester, undated; 2 (Box 2, Folder 122)
  - #140 Newnham College Library, 1908; 1 (Box 2, Folder 123)
  - #141 James Worsley Pennyman, undated; 3 (Box 2, Folder 124)
  - #142 William Duncan Simpson, undated; 2 (Box 2, Folder 125)
  - #144 Mabel St. Oswald, undated; 1 (Box 2, Folder 126)
  - #148 Maud Cator, undated; 1 (Box 2, Folder 127)
  - #154 C. R. L. E. Harvey, undated; 1 (Box 2, Folder 128)
  - #156 Alan Cecil Lupton, undated; 1 (Box 2, Folder 129)
  - #157 Thomas Horrocks Miller, undated; 3 (Box 2, Folder 130)
  - #158 Bertram Reveley Mitford, undated; 1 (Box 2, Folder 131)
  - #159 Charles Bine Renshaw, undated; 4 (Box 2, Folder 132)
  - #160 Matthew White, Viscount Ridley, 1909; 3 (Box 2, Folder 133)
  - #161 Hugh Western, undated; 1 (Box 2, Folder 134)
  - #162 Margaret Bigge, undated; 1 (Box 2, Folder 135)
  - #163 Ivy, undated; 1 (Box 2, Folder 136)
  - #166 Sir Ernest Cassel, 1910; 2 (Box 2, Folder 137)
  - #167 Daisy Charrington, undated; 2 (Box 2, Folder 138)
  - #169 Zoe Hoyle, undated; 1 (Box 2, Folder 139)
  - #171 Lionel Fortescue, Earl of Lovelace, 1910; 3 (Box 2, Folder 140)
  - #172 Ottilie Loring, undated; 1 (Box 2, Folder 141)
  - #173 William Newsam McClean, undated; 2 (Box 2, Folder 142)
  - #175 Ethel Mary Portal, undated; 2 (Box 2, Folder 143)
  - #176 George Henry Mildmay Ricketts, undated; 1 (Box 2, Folder 144)
  - #177 Matthew White, Viscount Ridley, 1910; 2 (Box 2, Folder 145)
  - #178 Sir Thomas Courtenay Theydon Warner, undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 146)
  - #179 Arthur Grenfell Wauchope, undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 147)
  - #180 Harold Wilmerding Bell, 1911; 4 (Box 3, Folder 148)
  - #181 Thomas B. Bowring, 1911; 2 (Box 3, Folder 149)
  - #182 John Arthur Brooke, undated; 3 (Box 3, Folder 150)
  - #183 William Richards Castle, 1911; 1 (Box 3, Folder 151)
  - #184 William Richards Castle (gift to Harvard Library College), 1911; 2 (Box 3, Folder 152)
  - #185 Rectory of St. Andrews Church, Coston, undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 153)
  - #186 Alexander Deneke, undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 154)
  - #188 Maxine Elliott, undated; 2 (Box 3, Folder 155)
  - #189 Hugh, Earl Fortescue, 1911; 1 (Box 3, Folder 156)
  - #190 Giles Stephen Holland, Earl of Ilchester, 1911; 2 (Box 3, Folder 157)
  - #191 Florence Leach, undated; 2 (Box 3, Folder 158)
  - #192 William Moseley Fenton Mellor, 1911; 2 (Box 3, Folder 159)
  - #193 Sir Alfred Mond, undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 160)
  - #194 Henrietta Frances May Tempest, undated; 2 (Box 3, Folder 161)
  - #195 Windsor Castle Library, undated; 2 (Box 3, Folder 162)
  - #196 Windsor Castle Library, 1911; 3 (Box 3, Folder 163)
  - #197 Windsor Castle Library, 1911; 2 (Box 3, Folder 164)
  - #198 Windsor Castle Library, 1911; 1 (Box 3, Folder 165)
  - #199 Charles Henry Ziegler, undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 166)
  - #200 Marion Beckett, undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 167)
  - #201 W. Heward Bell, 1902; 1 (Box 3, Folder 168)
  - #202 Edward Russell Bernard, 1912; 2 (Box 3, Folder 169)
  - #203 Frederick Copland-Griffiths, 1912; 2 (Box 3, Folder 170)
  - #204 Veronica Copland-Griffiths, 1912; 2 (Box 3, Folder 171)
  - #205 Dexter, 1912; 2 (Box 3, Folder 172)
  - #206 Franklin Dexter, 1912; 1 (Box 3, Folder 173)
  - #207 Gordon Dexter, 1912; 3 (Box 3, Folder 174)
  - #208 Ida and Hugh Fletcher-Moulton, undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 175)
  - #210 Warwick Greene, 1912; 2 (Box 3, Folder 176)
  - #211 Mabel Newton Hare, undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 177)
  - #212 Sir Boverton Redwood, 1912; 2 (Box 3, Folder 178)
  - #213 Frederick and Anne Dumville Richmond Brown, undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 179)
  - #215 William Eccles, 1913; 3 (Box 3, Folder 180)
  - #216 William Eccles, 1913; 4 (Box 3, Folder 181)
  - #217 Emily Fortescue, 1913; 2 (Box 3, Folder 182)
  - #218 "Albani Dni De Aldenham" (Gibs), 1913; 1 (Box 3, Folder 183)
  - #219 Juliet Pierpont Hamilton, undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 184)
  - #223 John Bickersteth Wheeler, undated; 3 (Box 3, Folder 185)
  - #225 Casilda Ince Anderton, undated; 3 (Box 3, Folder 186)
  - #226 Percy Neville Barnett, 1914; 11 items (Box 3, Folder 187)
  - #227 Charles Stewart Davison, 1914; 2 (Box 3, Folder 188)
  - #228 Edward J. F. Johnston, 1914; 2 (Box 3, Folder 189)
  - #229 Pierre De Chaignon La Rose, 1914; 2 (Box 3, Folder 190)
  - #230 Frederick Schenck, 1914; 4 (Box 3, Folder 191)
  - #231 Arthur Pickett Scott, 1914; 2 (Box 3, Folder 192)
  - #232 Pearl (Sharp), 1914; 2 (Box 3, Folder 193)
  - #233 Alfred Ashworth, undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 194)
  - #234 Philip H. Ashworth, undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 195)
  - #235 Otto Beit, undated; 2 (Box 3, Folder 196)
  - #238 Edward Frederick Chapman, undated; 2 (Box 3, Folder 197)
  - #242 Charles A. Hill, undated; 4 (Box 3, Folder 198)
  - #243 Frank G. House, undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 199)
  - #249 Henry B. Wheatley, undated; 7 (Box 3, Folder 200)
  - #251 Anonymous, undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 201)
  - #252 Frederick J. O. Montagu (Anonymous), undated; 2 (Box 3, Folder 202)
  - #254 Anonymous, undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 203)
  - #255 Marie Louise, undated; 4 (Box 3, Folder 204)
  - #256 Thompson, undated; 2 (Box 3, Folder 205)
  - #257 Anonymous, 1912; 3 (Box 3, Folder 206)
- Unnumbered Bookplates, Series II
  This series contains bookplates that were not included in the 1916 descriptive catalogue by Viner.
  Arranged alphabetically by the patron's last name. Any correspondence or ephemeral materials relating to a specific bookplate are filed together with the bookplate.
  - Aken L. Albright, undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 207)
  - Joseph M. Andreini, 1912; 1 (Box 3, Folder 208)
    A note on the mount states that this is a decorative proof by Eve that is not included in George Heath Viner's descriptive catalogue. The design is very similar to #204.
  - Sir Richard Barnett, undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 209)
  - George Langford Hamilton, undated; 2 (Box 3, Folder 210)
  - Althea L. House, undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 211)
  - Grolier Club, undated; 4 (Box 3, Folder 212)
  - Charles Laurie, S. C., undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 213)
  - Juliani Marshall, undated; 2 (Box 3, Folder 214)
  - Samuel Martin, 1912; 1 (Box 3, Folder 215)
  - Buchanan Winthrop, 1909; 2 (Box 3, Folder 216)
- Bookplates Attributed to Eve, Series III
  This series contains several bookplates that were housed together and labeled: "Attributed to Eve." Eve has been identified as the artist for each of these plates by the collector, Irene D. Andrews Pace.
  - Authors Club Library, undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 217)
  - A. H. F. Boughey, 1894; 1 (Box 3, Folder 218)
  - Christine, undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 219)
  - Susan Elizabeth Fortescue, undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 220)
  - Geoffrey Reginald Devereux Shaw, 1925; 1 (Box 3, Folder 221)
  - Rochfort Henry Sperling, undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 222)
  - John Black Stewart, undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 223)
  - William Henry Weldon, 1892; 1 (Box 3, Folder 224)
- Correspondence and Ephemera, Series IV
  - Ephemera, 1950 undated; 5 (Box 3, Folder 225)
    This folder contains a letter written by J. Sidney Pearson to Warren Hiram Lowenhaupt and a few handwritten checklists pertaining to these Eve materials.